<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marco Stefanucci</title>
    <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Marco Stefanucci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Powered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 16:39:17 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcostefanucci.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Locally sparse function-on-function regression</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/15/</guid>
      <description>CFE-CMStatistics 2021, December 2021, London (UK), Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The association between containment measures implemented by countries across the world and excess mortality linked to Covid-19: a study based on functional data analysis</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/14/</guid>
      <description>SELECT intermediate workshop, University of Venice, October 2021.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bernardi, M., Canale, A., Stefanucci, M., Locally Sparse Function-on-Function Regression. Submitted</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/14/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
In functional data analysis, functional linear regression has attracted significant attention recently. Herein, we consider the case where both the response and covariates are functions. There are two available approaches for addressing such a situation: concurrent and nonconcurrent functional models. In the former, the value of the functional response at a given domain point depends only on the value of the functional regressors evaluated at the same domain point, whereas, in the latter, the functional covariates evaluated at each point of their domain have a non-null effect on the response at any point of its domain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frizzarin, M., Bevilacqua, A., Dhariyal, B., Domijan, K., Ferraccioli, F., Hayes, E., Ifrim, G., Konkolewska, A., Nguyen, T.L., Mbaka, U., Ranzato, G., Singh, A., Stefanucci, M., Casa, A., Mid infrared spectroscopy and milk quality traits: a data analysis competition at the International Workshop on Spectroscopy and Chemometrics 2021. Chemometrics and Intelligent Laboratory Systems, 2021, 219.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/13/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
A chemometric data analysis challenge has been arranged during the first edition of the &amp;ldquo;International Workshop on Spectroscopy and Chemometrics&amp;rdquo;, organized by the Vistamilk SFI Research Centre and held online in April 2021. The aim of the competition was to build a calibration model in order to predict milk quality traits exploiting the information contained in mid-infrared spectra only. Three different traits have been provided, presenting heterogeneous degrees of prediction complexity thus possibly requiring trait-specific modelling choices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale stick-breaking mixture models</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/8/</guid>
      <description>ISBA 2021, June 2021, Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Locally sparse functional regression with an application to mortality data</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/7/</guid>
      <description>SIS 2021, June 2021, Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bernardi, M., Canale, A., Stefanucci, M., Locally sparse functional regression with an application to mortality data in Book of Short Papers SIS 2021. Pearson, 2021.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/6/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Melting Functional and Compositional data analysis to analyze mortality-by-cause trends</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/13/</guid>
      <description>Data Science and Scientific Computing, University of Trieste, June 2021, Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Cause-Specific Mortality Trends Using Compositional Functional Data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/6/</guid>
      <description>PAA 2021, May 2021, Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional data analysis: classification with missing and compositional data</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/12/</guid>
      <description>University of Rome Tor Vergata, March 2021, Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing cause-specific mortality trends using compositional functional data analysis</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/11/</guid>
      <description>UCD Working Group on Statistical Learning, October 2020, Online</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kraus, D., Stefanucci, M., Ridge reconstruction of partially observed functional data is asymptotically optimal. Statistics &amp; Probability Letters. 2020,165.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/10/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
When functional data are observed on parts of the domain, it is of interest to recover the missing parts of curves. Kraus (2015) proposed a linear reconstruction method based on ridge regularization. Kneip and Liebl (2019) argue that an assumption under which Kraus (2015) established the consistency of the ridge method is too restrictive and propose a principal component reconstruction method that they prove to be asymptotically optimal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overlap Group Lasso for Functional regression</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/5/</guid>
      <description>EMS 2019, July 2019, Palermo (IT)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Canale, A., Multiscale stick-breaking mixture models. Statistics and Computing, 2021, 31, 13.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/11/</guid>
      <description>Link to the paper
Abstract
Bayesian nonparametric density estimation is dominated by single-scale methods, typically exploiting mixture model specifications, exception made for Pólya trees prior and allied approaches. In this paper we focus on developing a novel family of multiscale stick-breaking mixture models that inherits some of the advantages of both single-scale nonparametric mixtures and Pólya trees. Our proposal is based on a mixture specification exploiting an infinitely deep binary tree of random weights that grows according to a multiscale generalization of a large class of stick-breaking processes; this multiscale stick-breaking is paired with specific stochastic processes generating sequences of parameters that induce stochastically ordered kernel functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Mazzuco, S., Analyzing cause-specific mortality trends using Compositional Functional Data Analysis. Accepted in Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series A</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/12/</guid>
      <description>Accepted in JRSSA.link to the paper
Abstract
We study the dynamics of cause-specific mortality rates among countries by considering them as compositions of functions. We develop a novel framework for such data structure, with particular attention to functional PCA. The application of this method to a subset of the WHO ùmortality database reveals the main modes of variation of cause-specific rates over years for men and women and enables us to perform clustering in the projected subspace.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Mazzuco, S., Inspecting cause-specific mortality curves by simplicial functional data analysis in Book of Short Papers SIS 2020. Pearson, 2020.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/5/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Multiscale Mixtures of Gaussian kernels for density estimation</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/10/</guid>
      <description>CFE-CMStatistics 2019, December 2019, London (UK)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kraus, D., Stefanucci, M., Classification of functional fragments by regularized linear classifiers with domain selection. Biometrika. 2019,106,1,161–180.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/9/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
We consider classification of functional data into two groups by linear classifiers based on one-dimensional projections of functions. We reformulate the task of finding the best classifier as an optimization problem and solve it by the conjugate gradient method with early stopping, the principal component method, and the ridge method. We study the empirical version with finite training samples consisting of incomplete functions observed on different subsets of the domain and show that the optimal, possibly zero, misclassification probability can be achieved in the limit along a possibly nonconvergent empirical regularization path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Canale, A., Bayesian multiscale mixture of Gaussian kernels for density estimation in Book of Short Papers SIS 2019. Pearson, 2019.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/4/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian multiscale mixture of Gaussian kernels for density estimation</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/4/</guid>
      <description>SIS 2019, June 2019, Milan (IT)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of functional fragments</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/3/</guid>
      <description>CFE-CMStatistics 2018, December 2018, Pisa (IT)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capozzo, A., Ferraccioli, F., Stefanucci, M., Secchi, P., An object oriented approach to Multimodal Imaging Data in Neuroscience, chapter in Studies in Neural Data Science. Springer, 2018.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/7/</guid>
      <description>chapter in &amp;ldquo;Studies in Neural Data Science&amp;rdquo;. Springer, 2018.link</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Little Bio</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/about/bio/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/about/bio/</guid>
      <description>I am an Assistant Professor in Statistics at the Department of Statistical Sciences, University of Rome - La Sapienza. Previously I was an assistant professor at University of Trieste and postdoctoral researcher at University of Padova. I obtained my PhD at University of Rome - La Sapienza under the supervision of professor Pierpaolo Brutti. During and after my PhD I had the chance to collaborate with other researchers, such as David Kraus, Laura Sangalli, Antonio Canale and Stefano Mazzuco.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci M., Sangalli L.M., Brutti P., Classification of the Aneurisk65 dataset using PCA for partially observed functional data in Book of Short Papers SIS 2018. Pearson, 2018.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci M., Sangalli L.M., Brutti P., PCA‐based discrimination of partially observed functional data, with an application to AneuRisk65 data set. Statistica Neerlandica. 2018,1–19.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/8/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
Functional data are usually assumed to be observed on a common domain. However, it is often the case that some portion of the functional data is missing for some statistical unit, invalidating most of the existing techniques for functional data analysis. The development of methods able to handle partially observed or incomplete functional data is currently attracting increasing interest. We here briefly review this literature. We then focus on discrimination based on principal component analysis and illustrate a few possible methods via simulation studies and an application to the AneuRisk65 data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PCA-based discrimination of partially observed functional data, with an application to Aneurisk65 dataset</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/2/</guid>
      <description>2nd CRoNoS Workshop on Functional Data Analysis, satellite event of COMPSTAT 2018, September 2018, Iasi (RO)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essential CV</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/about/essential-cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/about/essential-cv/</guid>
      <description>Contacts
Email: marco.stefanuc@gmail.com
 Current position
[2021+] Assistant Professor (RTDA)
Department of Statistical Sciences, University of Rome - La Sapienza
 Past positions
[2021-2021] Assistant Professor (RTDA)
Department of Business, Economics, Mathematics and Statistics &amp;ldquo;Bruno de Finetti&amp;rdquo;, University of Trieste
[2018-2021] Post Dosctoral researcher
Department of Statistical Sciences, University of Padua
 Education
[2015-2018] PhD in Methodological Statistics
Department of Statistical Sciences, University of Rome - La Sapienza
[2012-2015] Master of Science in Statistics</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regularized classification of functional fragments</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/talks/1/</guid>
      <description>CFE-CMStatistics 2017, December 2017, London (UK)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Collaborators</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/about/mycollaborators/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/about/mycollaborators/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve shared pain and gain with some other researchers in statistics-related fields, most of them are listed here.
Pierpaolo Brutti, associate professor at University of Rome - La Sapienza
Antonio Canale, associate professor at University of Padua
David Kraus, assistant professor at Masaryk University, Brno
Stefano Mazzuco, associate professor at University of Padua
Laura Sangalli, associate professor at Polictecnico di Milano</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
