<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Marco Stefanucci</title>
    <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Marco Stefanucci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Powered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Kraus, D., Stefanucci, M., Ridge reconstruction of partially observed functional data is asymptotically optimal. Statistics &amp; Probability Letters. 2020,165.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/10/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
When functional data are observed on parts of the domain, it is of interest to recover the missing parts of curves. Kraus (2015) proposed a linear reconstruction method based on ridge regularization. Kneip and Liebl (2019) argue that an assumption under which Kraus (2015) established the consistency of the ridge method is too restrictive and propose a principal component reconstruction method that they prove to be asymptotically optimal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Canale, A., Multiscale stick-breaking mixture models. Statistics and Computing, 2021, 31, 13.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/11/</guid>
      <description>Link to the paper
Abstract
Bayesian nonparametric density estimation is dominated by single-scale methods, typically exploiting mixture model specifications, exception made for Pólya trees prior and allied approaches. In this paper we focus on developing a novel family of multiscale stick-breaking mixture models that inherits some of the advantages of both single-scale nonparametric mixtures and Pólya trees. Our proposal is based on a mixture specification exploiting an infinitely deep binary tree of random weights that grows according to a multiscale generalization of a large class of stick-breaking processes; this multiscale stick-breaking is paired with specific stochastic processes generating sequences of parameters that induce stochastically ordered kernel functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Mazzuco, S., Analyzing cause-specific mortality trends using Compositional Functional Data Analysis. Accepted in Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series A</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/12/</guid>
      <description>Accepted in JRSSA.link</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Mazzuco, S., Inspecting cause-specific mortality curves by simplicial functional data analysis in Book of Short Papers SIS 2020. Pearson, 2020.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/6/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kraus, D., Stefanucci, M., Classification of functional fragments by regularized linear classifiers with domain selection. Biometrika. 2019,106,1,161–180.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/9/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
We consider classification of functional data into two groups by linear classifiers based on one-dimensional projections of functions. We reformulate the task of finding the best classifier as an optimization problem and solve it by the conjugate gradient method with early stopping, the principal component method, and the ridge method. We study the empirical version with finite training samples consisting of incomplete functions observed on different subsets of the domain and show that the optimal, possibly zero, misclassification probability can be achieved in the limit along a possibly nonconvergent empirical regularization path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci, M., Canale, A., Bayesian multiscale mixture of Gaussian kernels for density estimation in Book of Short Papers SIS 2019. Pearson, 2019.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/4/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capozzo, A., Ferraccioli, F., Stefanucci, M., Secchi, P., An object oriented approach to Multimodal Imaging Data in Neuroscience, chapter in Studies in Neural Data Science. Springer, 2018.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/7/</guid>
      <description>chapter in &amp;ldquo;Studies in Neural Data Science&amp;rdquo;. Springer, 2018.link</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci M., Sangalli L.M., Brutti P., Classification of the Aneurisk65 dataset using PCA for partially observed functional data in Book of Short Papers SIS 2018. Pearson, 2018.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stefanucci M., Sangalli L.M., Brutti P., PCA‐based discrimination of partially observed functional data, with an application to AneuRisk65 data set. Statistica Neerlandica. 2018,1–19.</title>
      <link>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 16:39:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcostefanucci.github.io/publications/8/</guid>
      <description>link to the paper
Abstract
Functional data are usually assumed to be observed on a common domain. However, it is often the case that some portion of the functional data is missing for some statistical unit, invalidating most of the existing techniques for functional data analysis. The development of methods able to handle partially observed or incomplete functional data is currently attracting increasing interest. We here briefly review this literature. We then focus on discrimination based on principal component analysis and illustrate a few possible methods via simulation studies and an application to the AneuRisk65 data set.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
